Michael A. Peszke Papers CPAA 91.15
Connecticut Polish American Archives
Michael A. Peszke Papers
1971-2013
CPAA 91.15
Connecticut Polish American Archives
1.0 Linear feet
Michael Alfred Peszke was born Poland in 1932. After the outbreak of WW II his family evacuated to France and England. Michael A. Peszke received his medical degree from the Dublin University School of Medicine, and in 1956 came to the US and worked in his field of psychiatry until his retirement in 1999. He combined clinical work with research, teaching, and administrative duties, and published widely in his field. After his retirement he turned to his interest in Poland and World War II. He published four books and numerous scholarly articles. Dr. Peszke is the founding member of the Polish Studies Program at Central Connecticut State University. His collection contains his scholarly articles, essays, and books and material which illustrate his interest in history and promotion of Poland, and his memoir written in 2006.
Peszke, Michael, Alfred
Biographical/Historical note
Michael Alfred Peszke, the son of a military hero of Poland, born in Deblin in 1932. After the outbreak of World War II and the Nazi and Soviet invasion of Poland, the Peszke family evacuated to France and Britain. Michael Alfred Peszke, after attending school in Scotland and England, studied at Trinity College, Dublin University, and the Dublin University School of Medicine, where he received his medical degree. From 1956 until his retirement in 1999, he combined clinical work with research, teaching, and administrative duties, chiefly on the East Coast of the United States. He has published widely and held a number of prestigious positions including a professorship at the University of Connecticut. After his retirement he turned to his real love, Poland and World War II, and produced a stunning four books on the subject dealing with military, diplomatic, and political history. He has supplemented these publications with a host of important articles. His number of publications far outstrips many life-long historians. Peszke's historical writings show particular strength in regard to the delicate wartime politics and diplomacy of a country tragically trapped between the aggressive imperialisms of western and eastern Europe, a country betrayed by her own wartime European and American allies. In addition his careers as physician and historian, he has had an enviable history as friend of Polish studies in the United States. He was one of the founding members of the Polish Studies Chair at Central Connecticut State University and has been a mainstay of the program as advisor and worker ever since. His contributions are most impressive. Michael Peszke has also served with other Polish organizations, including the Polish Institute of Arts and Sciences and Polish American Congress. In 2014 during the 40th Anniversary Gala of the Polish Studies Poragram, Dr Peszke received prestigious Bene Merito award from the Ministry of Foreogn Affairs of the Republic of Poland, for his work and contributions to promote Poand abroad. Michael A. Peszke, M.D. died suddenly and unexpectedly at his home in Wakefield, RI on May 17, 2015.
Conditions Governing Access note
The collection is open for research.
Custodial History note
The bulk of the material was given to the Connecticut Polish American Archives in 1991 an later publications were given as they were published.
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains published works by Michael Alfred Peszke. Also materials documenting activities of the Polish American Congress, Connecticut Division and the establishemnt of the Polish Studies Porgram at Central Connecticut State University. It also contains memoir written by M. Peszke documenting his earliest recollection from Poland, World War II, living in England after the War, attending medical school in Dublin, and immigrating to the US in 1956.
Poland - History, Naval - 20th century; Article; Poland - Armed Forces - History - World War, 1939-1945; Polish American Congress; Polish American Congress. Connecticut Division; Polish Americans -- Connecticut; World War, 1939-1945 - Underground movements - Poland; World War, 1939-1945 -- Poland
- Michael Alfred Peszke - resume, awards (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Passage to the New World, memoir written by Michael Alfred Peszke, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 1A)
- M. Peszke writings: Historiographic problems and issues in relations to the role of the Polish Air Force in the September 1939 campaign., 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- M. Peszke writings: Kosciuszko Remembered, Polish Air Force Squadron Badges; Battle of Britain statistics re-examined, copy of the article for AAHS Journal, Spring 1973. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- M. Peszke writings: The Polish-American Community: How Polish, how American, how much of a community?, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- M. Peszke writings: Operational Doctrine of the Polish Air Force in WWII; published in Aerospace Historian, September 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- M. Peszke writings: Love demands sacrifice: A History of Poland's Bomber Brigade, by Alfred B. Peszke and Michael A. Peszke, [1972] (Box 1, Folder 6)
- M. Peszke writings: Poland's Preparation for WWII, an article in Military Affairs, February 1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- M. Peszke writings: A Synopsis of Polish-Allied Military Agreements During World War II, an article published in Military Affairs, October 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- M. Peszke writings: The Polish Parachute Brigade in WWII, an article published in Military Affairs, October 1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- M. Peszke writings: Polish plans to give air support to the Polish Uprising, an article in International Collections of Military History, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- M. Peszke writings: The Polish Army in World War II, an article published in Sea Classics, March 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- M. Peszke writings: An Introduction to English-Language literature on the Polish Armed Forces in WWII, an essay published in The Journal of Military History, October 2006 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- M. Peszke writings: Poland's military aviation, September 1939: It never had a chance, chapter in the book "Why Air Forces Fail: The anatomy of defet", 2006 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- M. Peszke writings: Correspondence related to military orders of chivalry for Polish generals during WWII in Great Britain, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- M. Peszke writings: Polish special duties flight #1586 and the Warsaw Uprising, an article in Air Power History, Summer 2006 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- M. Peszke writings: The Polish Air Force in the United Kingdom, 1939-1946, an article in Air Power v. 11, no.3, Winter 2008 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- M. Peszke writings: No! The 303 Kosciuszko Squadron was not part of the RAF, (compilation of related historical documents) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- M. Peszke writings: One Thousand Years of Polish Military Uniform (notes to the power point presentation), 2010 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- M. Peszke writings: Poland's Military in World War II, a book chapter published in A Companion to World War II, vol. I, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- M. Peszke writings: The British-Polish Agreement of August 1940: its antecedents, siginficance and consequences, an essay in the Journal of Slavic Military Studies, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- M. Peszke book: The Polish Navy in the Second World War: A Historical Sketch, 1989 (Box 1, Object 1)
- M. Peszke book: Poland's Navy 1918-1945 (2 copies), 1999 (Box 1, Object 2)
- M. Peszke book: Battle For Warsaw 1939-1944, 1995 (Box 1, Object 3)
- Polish Studies Program at CCSU lobbying effort, 1970-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- State Resolution to Establish Polish Studies at CCSU. House Bill #9386 and supporting materials., 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Polish Studies Program at CCSU, reports and brochures., 1974-1984 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- PAC, Connecticut division - membership list. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- PAC National - reports, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- PAC, Connecticut Division - Bulletin 1971-1974 (scattered issues) (Box 2, Folder 6)
- PAC, Connecticut Division - Cultural and Educational committee, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- M. Peszke writings: "Totemism in Uniform and the Sarmatian Ideal" (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 9)